Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files, 1967-1991 UA.2.10.1967-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Academic Year 1969/70, III.
  - Student Affairs, 1969-1970; 7.0.
    - Student Affairs, 1969-1970; 7.1.
      - Tuition (Box 17, Folder 7.1.2)
      - Housing (Box 18, Folder 7.1.3)
        University Housing Office Resident Assistant Manual; Memo on Ten Year Housing Projections, August 20, 1969; Procedures Used to Contact and Communicate with Students in Residence; Security in the Towers Residential Complex; Housing Report, Fall Term, 1969, Oakland Campus; Graduate Housing, December 15, 1969; Open Hearing on Student Housing, March 5, 1970; and "Fraternity Complex Feasibility Study for University of Pittsburgh."
      - Student Union (Box 18, Folder 7.1.4)
        Security at Pitt Student Union; University Event and Activity Information; Admittance Policy, Pitt Student Union; and Statement of Congratulations from Chancellor to finalists in the Miss University of Pittsburgh Competition.
      - Student Health Service (Box 18, Folder 7.1.5)
    - Student Organizations, 1969-1970; 7.2.
      - Organizations - General (Box 18, Folder 7.2)
      - Student Government (Box 18, Folder 7.2.2)
    - Demonstrations (Campus Unrest), 1969-1970; 7.3.
      - Demonstrations (Box 18, Folder 7.3)
    - Activities, 1969-1970; 7.4.
      - Activities - General (Box 18, Folder 7.4)
      - Commencement (Box 18a, Folder 7.4.1)
        Letters from President Nixon and Henry Kissinger and Letter to John Cardinal Wright.
      - Honorary Degrees (Box 18a, Folder 7.4.2)
        Chronological List of Honorary Degrees, 1849-1969; Honorary Degree Candidates; Memos regarding One Undergraduate Student to serve as member of Ad Hoc Committee to nominate candidates for Honorary Degree; and Report of Meeting of University Committee on Honorary Degrees.
      - Homecoming (Box 19, Folder 7.4.3)
    - Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC), 1969-1970; 7.5.
      - ROTC (Box 19, Folder 7.5)
        ROTC Enrollment, May 7, 1970; Report of FAS Committee to Study ROTC, May 28, 1970; and Recommendation for the Award of the Legion of Merit to Col. David C. Clagett, Professor of Military Science, July 9, 1969
    - Selective Service, 1969-1970; 7.6.
      - Press Releases (Box 19, Folder 7.6)
    - Scholarships and Awards, 1969-1970; 7.7.
      - Correspondence and Booklet (Box 19, Folder 7.7)
    - Placement Service, 1969-1970; 7.8.
      - Placement (Box 19, Folder 7.8)
  - Pamphlets and Miscellaneous, 1969-1970; 8.0.
    - Memoranda (Box 19, Folder 8.0.)
      "Agenda for the next President of the U.S.," Pittsburgh World Affairs Council, May 28, 1968; Proposal for a Fourth International Symposium on Arms Control, June 17, 1969; An Open Letter to All Members of the CMU Campus Community, September 5, 1969; Mellon Student Art Study Program; Dr. Posvar to receive a Doctor of Laws Degree from Temple University; Pamphlets from School of Engineering, Civil Engineering, Electrical Engineering, and Industrial, Chemical, Petroleum, Mechanical, Metallurgical and Materials Engineering; and Self-Evaluation Reports on The School, Undergraduate Education, and Graduate Programs
    - Pamphlets and Reports (Box 19, Folder 8.0a)
- Academic Year 1970/71, IV.
  - Academic Programs, 1970-1971; 1.0.
    - Academic Programs - General, 1970-1971; 1.0.
      - Academic Programs (Box 1, Folder 1.0.)
        Report of the Chancellor's Committee on the Future of the Arts; The Need for a Learning Skills Center, Environmental Control Measures; University of Pittsburgh's Division of Instructional Experimentation; An Abstract of a Proposal to Operate an Educational Development Center at UP Johnstown with a Major Emphasis on Ecology and Environmental Education; Proposal for a Workshop to Develop a Program on Conflict Resolution and Peace Studies; and Academic Calendar, 1971-1972.
    - New Careers Development Program, 1970-1971; 1.1.
      - Memoranda, Reports and Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1.1)
    - Middle States Evaluation, 1970-1971; 1.2.
      - Reports and Memoranda (Box 1, Folder 1.2)
      - Correspondence Regarding Middle States Team Visit (Box 1, Folder 1.2a)
    - Provost, 1970-1971; 1.3.
      - Provost - General (Box 1, Folder 1.3)
        Setting Up Caribbean Studies Program; Suggestions to establish a one-year Advanced Study Program for older black faculty and administrators from predominantly black colleges and universities; Joseph Katz Exhibition at the Frick; Multi-College Structure for Undergraduate Arts and Sciences; Interim Report on the Andrew Mellon Professors and Fellows; Proposed Agreement with Carnegie Museum; 3-M Studies Program; and Letter from Dr. Peter Gray regarding Senate Council.
    - Faculty of Arts and Sciences (FAS), 1970-1971; 1.4.
      - FAS - General (Box 1, Folder 1.4)
        Dr. Posvar letter regarding plans and prospects for a program in Judaic Studies, June 4, 1971; Memos regarding Report of the Chancellor's Committee on the Future of the Arts; Report of the Board of Visitors of FAS, December 4-5, 1970; Proposed Establishment of a Department of History and Philosophy of Science in the FAS; Policy Statements by the Committee of the University Art Gallery, 1970-1971; and Dr. Posvar letter granting conditional approval of Department of History and Philosophy of Science, June 24, 1971.
        New English Composition Program for September 1971; Pitt Release regarding Max Lauffer Named Department Chairman of Department of Biophysics and Microbiology, January 22, 1971; Multi-College Structure for Undergraduate Arts and Sciences, A Proposal for the University of Pittsburgh, November 15, 1970; Report of the FAS Committee on ROTC, May 28, 1970; FAS Productivity and Cost Analysis; Departmental Status for Black Studies; and Annual Report of Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1969-1970.
      - Future of the Arts (Box 1, Folder 1.4a)
      - College of Arts and Sciences (Box 1, Folder 1.4.1)
        Multi-College Structure for Undergraduate Arts and Sciences, A Proposal for the University of Pittsburgh, Revised December 24, 1970; Determination of Upper and Lower Level Course Percentages for Recent Graduates from the College of Arts and Sciences; Professional Opportunity Plan; The Universities and Society; "Survey of CAS Students, Preliminary Report, Change in CAS Enrollment, 1969-1970 to 1970-1971; Admissions to the CAS, 1971-1972; and Memo regarding CAS considering a proposal to establish a new four-year undergraduate degree program, the degree to be tentatively called "Bachelor of Philosophy".
      - Graduate Programs (Box 2, Folder 1.4.2)
        Membership Roster of 1971-1972 University Council on Graduate Study and Proposed Reorganization of Graduate Study.
      - School of General Studies (SGS) (Box 2, Folder 1.4.3)
        Steele Gow assumes position of Dean of the School of General Studies; Letter from A. Fedel to John Edgar Hoover with newspaper clippings; Memo regarding Office of Continuing Education, March 1, 1971; General Studies Prospectus, April 6, 1971; ASTRA, A Publication for SGS Students, December 1970; Memo on Developments in the School of General Studies, November 19, 1970; Memo regarding a report of the SGS Review Committee; June 3, 1970; Letter to Dean Viers Adams upon his retirement from University of Pittsburgh and Dean SGS, July 13, 1970; Memo regarding Progress Report of SGS Programs, January 19, 1971; and "Message From the Acting Dean" (Arthur Fedel).
    - Graduate School of Business (GSB), 1970-1971; 1.5.
      - Memoranda and Booklet (Box 2, Folder 1.5)
        The Mervis Bequest; Undergraduate Education for Business; Address by Mr. Jack E. Freeman to the University of Pittsburgh School of Business Alumni; Accreditation Report of Graduate School of Business; Executive Master's Program; and Minority Group Programs and Recruitment of Black Students.
    - School of Education, 1970-1971; 1.6.
      - School of Education - General (Box 2, Folder 1.6)
        Telegram from Dean Paul H. Masoner to President Richard M. Nixon regarding student unrest, May 13, 1970; Grant on Problems of School Desegregation; Agreement between City of Pittsburgh and University of Pittsburgh, Model Cities Program; Federal grant to develop and offer an educational program on drug abuse; and Research and Training Center in Vocation Rehabilitation, School of Education.
      - Falk School (Box 2, Folder 1.6.1)
        Proposals for early childhood opportunities related to Falk School; Request for re-evaluation of application for aid to Falk School as a non-public school; Correspondence on The Falk School Affair; Office of Governmental Relations suggested strategy for the Falk-University-Community Controversy; and Letters regarding Falk School Playground Area, with charts.
    - School of Engineering, 1970-1971; 1.7.
      - School of Engineering - General (Box 2, Folder 1.7)
        Dedication of Benedum Hall; Dedication of The George M. Bevier Engineering Library; Chancellor's Medal to Mr. and Mrs. George M. Bevier; Report of Board of Visitors, School of Engineering; Annual Report, School of Engineering, 1969-1970; Michael L. Benedum Hall of Engineering Guide; "School of Engineering: Past, Present and Future"; 4th Gwilym A. Price Engineering Lecture" "Nothing for Nothing"; Proposal for the Establishment of The William Kepler Whiteford Professorship of Energy Resources Development and Management in the School of Engineering, submitted to the Gulf Oil Company by the University of Pittsburgh; and Letter regarding Environmental Engineering Program.
    - School of Law, 1970-1971; 1.8.
      - Memoranda and Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1.8)
        Letter to members of Board of Visitors regarding new School of Law building, January 14, 1971, and Memo regarding Conferral of the degree of Juris Doctor on Judge Robert H. Rial of Court of Common Pleas, November 12, 1970.
    - Graduate School of Library and Information Science (GSLIS), 1970-1971; 1.9.
      - Memoranda (Box 2, Folder 1.9)
        The Science Library of Pittsburgh and Memo announcing Dr. Frank B. Sessa, Chairman of Department of Library Science, will be Acting Dean of GSLIS, April 20, 1971.
    - Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA), 1970-1971; 1.10.
      - Memoranda and Reports (Box 3, Folder 1.10.)
        Memo regarding Reappointment of Donald Stone for 1972-1973; "Proposed State Budget Allocations for Continuing Education and Extension Services," a Working Paper by Donald C. Stone, April 1971; Arguments against moving the GSPIA Library; ACE Staff Evaluation and Critique of the Arguments Presented by Professor E. J. Sternglass Concerning Infant Mortality and Nuclear Tests, December 1969; and Preparation of Population Program Administrators, A Request to the Jessie Smith Noyes Foundation.
    - Graduate School of Social Work (GSSW), 1970-1971; 1.11.
      - GSSW - General (Box 3, Folder 1.11)
        Proposed Undergraduate Program in Social Work; Report of the Senate Committee on Educational Policy; Letter regarding Commission on Accreditation of the Council on Social Work Education, May 7, 1971; the accredited status of the master's degree program offered by GSSW at Pitt; Report from Dr. Alfred J. Kahn, "Faculty Resources, University of Pittsburgh, GSSW," 2nd Draft, March 15, 1971; Summary of proposals for a black technical assistance center; Dr. William H. McCullough to retire from deanship of GSSW; Dr. James A. Goodman offered position of Dean of GSSW; Report from Alfred J. Kahn, on Two-Day Consultation at GSSW; and Report on GSSW Enrollment, Financial Aid and Student Body Characteristics, October 1, 1970.
    - Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC), 1970-1971; 1.12.
      - Correspondence and Report (Box 3, Folder 1.12)
        Report to the Board of Visitors, LRDC, February 1971, and Correspondence regarding Dr. JoAnn Gardner.
    - Space Research Coordination Center (SRCC), 1970-1971; 1.13.
      - Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 3, Folder 1.13)
        Letter regarding Pitt associates selected as the spectroscopy team for the Grand Tour of the Outer Planets Mission, April 14, 1971, with copy of TWX from NASA. Memo regarding New Name for the SRCC Building, suggesting the name "The Reginald A. Fessenden Hall," March 5, 1971.
    - Health Professions, 1970-1971; 1.14.
      - Health Professions - General, 1.14.
        - Pamphlets and Reports (Box 3, Folder 1.14)
          Constitution and By-Laws of the Medical Staff of the Hospital and Clinical Service Activities of the Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic of the University of Pittsburgh, adopted July 2, 1970; Annual Report of the Pittsburgh Child Guidance Center, 1969-1970; "Sights and Sounds" Annual Report of the Eye and Ear Hospital of Pittsburgh; "The First Seventy-five Years, a history of the Eye and Ear Hospital of Pittsburgh" Pamphlet; and Purpose of Arsenal Family and Children's Center for the Division of Instructional Experimentation.
      - School of Medicine, 1.14.1.
        - School of Medicine - General (Box 3, Folder 1.14.1)
          The family of the late Dr. William Mattuck Brinton donate a charcoal portrait of Dr. Brinton to the School of Medicine; Board of Visitors Meeting, May 7, 1971; Letter regarding Pitt School of Medicine as one of eight leading medical schools in country to share in grant from Commonwealth Fund for joint planning project, April 26, 1971; Letter of questions posed regarding Medical Science Building; Letter from Dean D. Medearis regarding medical education; The Dickson Prize in Medicine of the University of Pittsburgh presented to Earl W. Sutherland, Jr., M.D., Professor of Physiology, Vanderbilt University, October 12, 1970; and Joint Memorandum to the members of the Faculty of the Department of Biochemistry of FAS and the School of Medicine, July 17, 1970.
        - Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic (WPIC) (Box 3, Folder 1.14.1.1)
          Special Report on WPIC commitment to an Affirmative Action Program for Equal Employment Opportunity, November 3, 1970; Memo on Responsibilities for Administration of WPIC, September 18, 1970; Announcement of death of Bertram D. Lewin, M.D., Visiting Professor of Psychoanalysis; and Minutes of Meetings of WPIC Administrative Committee.
        - Executive Committee, Faculty of Medicine, Meeting Minutes (Box 3, Folder 1.14.1.2)
      - Graduate School of Public Health (GSPH), 1.14.2.
        - GSPH - General (Box 3, Folder 1.14.2)
          Memo regarding Proposal to I.W. Abel that the School sponsor a training program in occupational safety and health for United Steelworkers, April 19, 1971; Pitt Release announcing Hershel E. Griffin, M.D., Dean, GSPH, Elected President of Public Health Association, March 19, 1971; and Evaluation, The Health Professions and Public Problems, GSPH.
      - Dental Medicine, 1.14.3.
        - Dental Medicine - General (Box 4, Folder 1.14.3)
          Congratulatory letter from Dr. Posvar to Dean Forrest and the School of Dental Medicine on school's 75th Anniversary; "Facts about the University of Pittsburgh's School of Dental Medicine, Founded 1896-1971"; Pitt Release regarding Pitt Dental School to Hold 75th Anniversary Program, with preliminary and tentative program for the anniversary and copies of invitations for ceremonies and dinner, February 3, 1971; Dr. W. Harry Archer awarded the Rene Le Fort Medal, the highest decoration of the Colegio Brasileiro de Cirurgia e Traumatologia Buco-Maxilo-Facial of Brazil, July 22, 1970, with photos; and Annual Reports, "Smoking and Health Project," 1970-1971 and 1969-1970.
      - School of Pharmacy, 1.14.4.
        - Reports of the American Council on Pharmaceutical Education and Visiting Committee (Box 4, Folder 1.14.4)
      - School of Nursing, 1.14.5.
        - Report of Survey Made of the Undergraduate Nursing Program, July 30, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1.14.5)
      - School of Health Related Professions (SHRP), 1.14.6.
        - SHRP - General (Box 4, Folder 1.14.6)
          Proposed agenda for January Meeting of Board of Visitors with list of members, January 7, 1971; Community Relations Committee Meeting with document outlining how the Community Relations Council might function and list of Community Relations Council Committee, January 20, 1971; and Letter regarding establishment of prize account named for Dr. Jessie Wright of Department of Physical Therapy, October 7, 1970.
    - Regional Campuses, 1970-1971; 1.15.
      - Regional Campuses - General (Box 4, Folder 1.15)
        Draft Proposal for Task Forces to Provide Vertical Integration Among Community Colleges, Area Colleges and The University; Report to the Faculty, Administration, Trustees of The University of Pittsburgh Regional Campuses by An Evaluation Team representing the Commission on Higher Education of the Middle States Association; Comments on Middle States Association Draft Report on the Regional Campuses; Memo regarding Comments on Proposal for Graduate Education at Regional Campuses, March 10, 1971; Minutes of Provost's Committee on Regional Campuses, February 11, 1971; Memos regarding Proposed Regional Campuses Faculty Senate By-Laws; Tuition Subsidy; Provost's Committee on Regional Campuses; Statement of Operations for each Regional Campus; and Regional Campuses of the University of Pittsburgh Bulletin, 1969-1970.
      - Bradford Campus (Box 4, Folder 1.15.1)
        Emery Hotel purchased by the University for Bradford Campus and Organization and Procedures Committee Minutes, January 28, 1971.
      - Johnstown Campus (Box 4, Folder 1.15.3)
        Chancellor's Remarks at the Dedication of the Library, June 13, 1971; Dr. James M. Hester, President of New York University receives an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters Degree from UPJ; Special Cornerstone Edition of The Panther, September 11, 1970; "The Dedication of the New Campus Library of UPJ"; The Laying of the Cornerstone for the Library at UPJ; Renaming of North Hall to Walter M. Krebs Hall and renaming of South Hall to Theodore W. Biddle Hall; Advisory Board, UPJ, January 1970; Letter from David H. Kurtzman to Dr. Posvar regarding approval from State Board of Education at its January 15 meeting for conversion of the present Johnstown Campus to Johnstown College within the University of Pittsburgh, January 20, 1971; "A Projected Development of the Johnstown Regional Campus to a Four-Year Program as an Integral Part of the University of Pittsburgh of the Commonwealth System of Higher Education," presentation to the Council of Higher Education of the Pennsylvania State Board of Education, November 17, 1970; Engineering Technology at Johnstown, August 13, 1970; and Jack E. Freeman is offered position of President of UPJ effective July 1, 1971.
    - International Program, 1970-1971; 1.16.
      - International Program - General (Box 4, Folder 1.16)
      - University Center for International Studies (UCIS) (Box 4, Folder 1.16.1)
        Report on the first seven months (Phase I) of the Leadership Training Project; Memo to Dr. Posvar with Draft copy of By-Laws of the Pennsylvania Council for International Education; Proposal for a Program of Inter-Institutional Cooperation Between The Centre for Economic Development and Administration of Nepal and The University of Pittsburgh; "The Dilemma of Dissidence"; "International Newsletter," Winter-Spring 1970-1971; "Outline of Czech Morphology" by Charles E. Bidwell.; UCIS Activities, August-November 1970; and Annual Report on Inter-university Teaching and Training Program in Comparative Communism, 1969-1970.
    - Urban Programs, 1970-1971; 1.17.
      - Reports and Memoranda (Box 4, Folder 1.17)
        Progress reports on the Hill District-South Oakland Psychology Center; UUIP Sub-project in Hill District Psychology Center for Primary Prevention; Hill District Psychology Center: Revised Model Cities Proposals and Report of Progress; A Proposal to Model Cities for support of Hill District Psychology Center for Primary Prevention, submitted by Department of Psychology, University of Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh Model Cities Program, November 9, 1970 and July 2, 1970; NAACP statement on Campus Unrest; and Model Cities Grant for Professor O.K. Moore.
    - Research Programs, 1970-1971; 1.18.
      - Proposal to Establish the Pittsburgh Human Services Research Center and the "Official University Policy on Patents" (Box 4, Folder 1.18)
  - Athletics, 1970-1971; 2.0.
    - Athletics - General (Box 5, Folder 2.0.)
      Memo regarding Proposed Reorganization of the University's Athletic Committee, June 24, 1971; Athletes Reception at Chancellor's Residence, December 6, 1970; Announcement of summer program in swimming, gymnastics, and athletic activities for children of the faculty and administrative personnel; Article Three, Principles for the Conduct of Intercollegiate Athletics; The Trees Hall Center for the Development of Activity Programs for the Exceptional; and Draft Statement on Athletics and Black Athletes.
    - Director (Box 5, Folder 2.1)
      Curriculum vita of Albert E. Smith; Varsity Letter Club; Pitt Varsity Letter Club elected officers for year 1970-1971; Football; 1970 Pitt Football Guide; Official Program for Pitt-West Virginia, Homecoming, October 17, 1970; and Guest Lists for all Pitt games.
  - University Boards, Committees and Memberships, 1970-1971; 3.0.
    - Board of Trustees, 1970-1971; 3.1.
      - Board of Trustees - General (Box 5, Folder 3.1)
        Committees, Board of Trustees, 1970-1971; Dr. Posvar addresses the University Senate and presents a six-point list of requirements and needs for faculty participation; Statement of the three State-Related Universities, Penn State, Temple and Pitt, on the Proposed 1970 Master Plan for Higher Education; Dr. Posvar's memo to members of the Board of Trustees reviewing his administration of Pitt since becoming Chancellor, August 18, 1969; Chancellor's Reports and Agendas for Board of Trustees Meetings; Minutes of the Academic Affairs Committee Meeting of the Boards of Trustees, Johnstown Campus, May 13, 1970 and the Greensburg Campus, May 12, 1971; Trustee photographs and short biographies; and Dr. David H. Kurtzman Portrait Budget.
      - Budget-Audit Committee (Box 5, Folder 3.1.2)
      - Student Affairs Committee (Box 5, Folder 3.1.4)
      - Committee on the Health Professions (Box 5, Folder 3.1.5)
      - Executive Committee (Box 5, Folder 3.1.6)
        Facilities Committee Status Report, March 31, 1971; Faculty Second Mortgages; William Watson Smith Bequest; Executive Committee Vote on Provost and Proposal to Confer Honorary Degree on Governor Shapp; Anna Margaret Sloan and Mary Sloan Scholarship; Health Center Land Bank; LRDC Building; Naming Assembly Hall at Allegheny Observatory; Resolution to Dissolve Ruskin Corporation; Memos regarding University Organization; Educational Policies Committee Report to Senate Council, May 10, 1971; Honorary Degrees; Executive Committee, 1970-1971; and Bradford Dormitory Project.
      - Facilities Committee (Box 6, Folder 3.1.7)
        Facilities Committee Meeting Agendas and Minutes; Facilities Committee Status Reports of February 18, 1971 and December 4, 1970; and Memo regarding Future Use of the Stadium Area, May 4, 1970.
      - Financial Development Committee (Box 6, Folder 3.1.8)
      - Investment Committee (Box 6, Folder 3.1.9)
      - University Governance (Box 6, Folder 3.1.10)
        Current Materials on Changes in Institutional Governance and Control of Campus Disorders; Prevention and Control of Campus Disorder, Measure for Possible Conference-Seminar Consideration; and Civil Defense Organization, A Suggested Checklist of Short-Range Security Provisions.
    - Regional Campuses, 1970-1971; 3.2.
      - Bradford (Box 6, Folder 3.2.1)
      - Greensburg (Box 6, Folder 3.2.2)